There is nothing worse than not knowing
what to make content about.
You sit there,
you get in front of a camera,
and you just draw a blank.
So I'm going to go through some strategies
and methods that I use when it comes to
content creation.
The first thing we need to do
and ask ourself is what is it we
want?
Sometimes I might look at a pie chart of
the performance of the business the
month before,
look at the different offerings
and products I'm selling, and the
easiest thing we can do
is just make a list.
So I have my business mentorship for
$2,500, Content Mastery for
$99, and PT Starter Kit for $99.
So the first thing I could think about
is, is there a piece of content
that I want to make
that sends people to one of
these products? Now, although
that can be effective, sometimes it's like
going up to someone on the dance floor
and saying, "Yo, do you want to suck my
penis?" One in 100 people might say,
"Do you know what?
I bloody well do want to suck your penis."
But sometimes it's better for us to
strategize maybe being a little bit more
chivalrous and saying, "Can I buy you a
drink first?" So rather than getting to
this stage, I might look to the stage
before it.
You'll often hear me promote in videos
about 30 ways in 30 days
to benefit your business.
There's a link for
that in every single video that I've
done,
and that video has automated 30 emails
that pretty much just convince
people I know what I'm on about.
Roughly between days 19 and 21, they buy.
Recently, there's been another one.
You'll notice that recently I've been
doing a lot of content critiques.
The reason that these are doing well
is it gives me some unpolished,
off-the-cuff
time to go through people's sales systems
and processes and give them honest
feedback. Now,
the beautiful thing about this is
when people apply for a critique,
I add them to the 30-day autoresponder.
Now, weirdly, and interestingly enough,
the people that come in through critiques
and then go into the 30-day autoresponder
are attributing double the amount of
sales than just sending them to the 30-day
autoresponder.
So recently,
I've been doubling down on videos
that do that purely because when
they come through,
they're twice more likely to buy.
Now, on top of these things, there
are some other strategies in
which we might be
looking at.
I might also just put content out with the
pure objective of growth.
For that, we might use social hacking.
Maybe I'm going to put someone famous in
the thumbnail.
Maybe I'm going to hold up a book
that everyone's heard of and use that.
Sometimes the strategy
is just to get new people through the
door.
For YouTube growth,
probably going to use that.
However, for Instagram,
I'm probably going to use a slightly
different tactic.
The fact I've got 1.4 million people on my
Instagram, the majority of them aren't
going to be right for business mentoring
or whatever.
But my growth strategy for that
is usually just cross-promoting some of
the stuff
I'm doing to the main page.
So before we even have an ideation of
content or what
we're going to talk about,
we must look at the objective
that we want to get from
that piece of content.
Is it to send people to a landing page
where
hopefully some of them do business with
us?
Or is the smarter strategy going to be
about getting that person's contact
information by giving them something of
value?
So Declan,
what should we make today's video about?
Which one of these things appeals to you
the most? You want to go for growth.
Now, what should we grow?
You want to go with the YouTube
or the Instagram?
Well, we've already done-
Let's go YouTube. Cool.
It's kind of annoying because if you
were to pick any of the email
autoresponders,
I probably would make more money
because then we could email people,
put them in. But you said YouTube growth.
Sure.
Declan,
let's go for a vanity metric because at
the end of the day, you just like
making nice YouTube videos. Fine.
So we're going to have to begin with
packaging.
So for this video, let's go thumbnail
and title.
Now,
one thing that a YouTube strategist said
online, which I really liked the
other day,
which we could actually do today,
is to strategize up to 40 different
titles.
So before we get into the thumbnail,
let's think about some
titles for this video.
How to break through a content plateau.
Don't like the word plateau.
What's the words that I've been loving
recently? Superlatives.
Give me a list of all the superlatives
that you know. I learned that word,
and now I can't stop.
So here's some of the superlatives.
We've got best, worst, biggest, smallest,
fastest, oldest, youngest, richest,
poorest, hottest, coldest, loudest,
brightest, darkest,
heaviest, meanest, fastest. Ooh, I do like
fastest.
So maybe we could start with that.
Fastest way to- Fastest way. Best.
Fastest way.
The fastest way to come up to get
best content ideas.
Now this needs a bit of work.
The fastest way to get the best content
ideas. Maybe that's too many superlatives.
Let's try fastest way to generate
content ideas. Still feels a bit too long.
Content ideas.
Maybe we start with content.
Maybe we go the easiest, or easy and fast.
What about this?
Easy and fast content ideas.
But then again, I quite
like what you said about the story about
what we're doing.
We're trying to break through a content
plateau. It's got to be succinct though.
Fastest. Fastest way.
But we're not trying to break the
algorithm.
This video is centered around content
ideation.
Because if we go with that,
then the very first thing we said in this
video is not
going to make sense. We
are breaking our own rule here of not
doing the title and
thumbnail first.
Maybe we should go with the easiest.
Fast content ideas.
Fast content ideation.
But I want it to be real simple.
I want everyone to be able to understand
this title.
No,
it'd be weird because that's not what the
video is about.
It's about- [inaudible] No,
it's about getting good content ideas.
What about smartest? Fastest,
you're right, is good.
Fastest way to get. Fastest way for.
Maybe use the word viral. Viral ideas.
Viral ideas.
Fastest way to think of viral ideas.
How to get viral ideas fast.
Fastest way to think of viral content.
Fastest way.
People are going to get real insight to
what? I do like a superlative.
Easiest. Do people want fast
or do they want easy?
I'd like to use the word viral,
but I want to make it still around content
ideas.
Let's have a look if there's anything out
there. Blueprint.
Viral content ideas. Let's have a look
if there's anything that's been
working.
How to get video ideas so good you can't
stop going viral.
Oh, that is good.
How to get video ideas so good you can't
stop getting viral.
And the title fits. How about this?
How to get video ideas so fast you can't
stop
going viral. I like that. He says so good.
Five ways to get viral video ideas every
YouTuber should know.
How to trick the algorithm. No.
How to make shorts
that go viral every time. No.
How to actually grow on social media.
That one's quite good.
How to get viral ideas.
How to get content ideas so good you can't
stop going
viral. Hold on. How to get video ideas so
good you can't stop going viral. How
is that fitting in that?
That seems to me like a really long title.
It fits though.
Now, I like his light bulb.
So how about this?
How about, and this
is not going to be a bit of a rubbish
reveal for people, but
why don't I look to the camera,
we take a screen grab.
Maybe something like I think we put the
light bulb behind me, like a halo effect
behind my head. So the light,
nothing signifies
an idea more than a light bulb.
So have you got enough depth here?
So if I give you that shot. Yeah.
And maybe I could be like
Put that light bulb behind.
We'll go one more time.
People are going to really see what it's
like behind there.
Keep all this stuff in there as well.
Cool.
So there we've got a light bulb,
and then it'll be...
So that packaging,
I think it's going to be good.
So then we've got an intro.
So then as far as ideating this,
how would we go
about optimizing it?
So one thing we could definitely look at,
we've got
the long form, which
is going to be this video,
but then we should probably do a
short form for it as well. Now,
what I would say the steps are for
both of these when it comes to getting
good ideas, first of all, work
backwards.
Without knowing what the end thing is
that you want from
a video,
this one being about getting a little bit
more growth to a wider audience,
even though all the links will be to the
description, it's very difficult to know
what to talk about
or what you're going to entail it into.
Two, the first thing for YouTube
is going to be packaging, because
without getting those components right,
you're just not going to get there.
The third thing is to see what's working,
because the reason that we're able
to get a working title from this video
is we've got a proof of concept from
someone
else. Now, the one golden rule
that I would say with this is,
if you're going to
lever the see what's working category,
don't watch the video.
Because if we watch the video,
we could end up seeing an amazing hook
or an amazing
setup or an amazing title,
and I think that would be Leo out there
with your 135,000 subscribers.
We thank you very much for the title
inspiration.
We thank you very much for the thumbnail
inspiration, but we're not
going to steal any more from you.
So we've got that.
We've shown that we've now got a title
and thumbnail that we're going to run
with,
that we're going to put together.
We've got the work backwards,
we've got the
packaging,
we've got to see what's working.
Then what I would say for the majority of
creators out there, you have a good idea
for long format,
it's now time to turn
that into a 60-second reel,
which we're now going to do, Declan,
in this.
And then from the stuff in this,
we're going to have what it takes for
having a
reel. Now, this 60-second reel, Declan,
we actually could just do straight down
the barrel. We don't need the whiteboard,
because I know you're already thinking
about cropping me in for 1080. No, what
is it, 1080, 929?
1080 is the resolution. 1920 by whatever.
Okay.
So let's start thinking about a hook
that would be good, because on the long
format,
we're going to need an introduction,
which was a bit of an Unagi
inception for this one,
because it's part of it.
Okay, so we need a hook
that speaks to the person that's
struggling with the
problem. Let's think of a question hook.
I reckon we go with something like this.
Do you ever sit down to record content,
and then the moment you're ready to press
record, suddenly you've got no ideas
and you don't even know what to talk
about?
Then we can start doing the B-roll for
this.
So do you ever sit down to record content,
and then the moment you're ready to
press record,
suddenly you've got no ideas
and you don't even know what to talk
about? So there we've just done the hook,
the B-roll.
Then let's think of a type of unknown
setup.
Well, don't be sad. Cheer up,
because in this video,
we're going to go through a
three-stage solution that's going to
ensure that every time you have a content
block,
you can have some actionable things
that you can do to ensure you can put
out a piece of content today
that benefits your business.
Maybe a little bit more B-roll.
We could be like...
We're just having some fun at the moment.
So then we said that the three-stage thing
was, first of all, work backwards.
What's cool is when we put this reel
together on social, people that have
seen the long format will know where it's
come from.
People who see the short format won't.
Work backwards.
We said, see what's working. What
was the second thing we said before,
Declan?
Let's have a little look. This
is why we take pictures of things.
Packaging.
Now, I will admit,
those of you on short form content care
way too much
about the packaging. People
are spending 10,
15 minutes creating a thumbnail for an
Instagram reel. No one cares,
because I guarantee people are doing
this.
This is how people
are discovering your reels.
They are not scrolling your page
and looking at your thumbnails, or
if they are,
they're not doing it at a meaningful
amount for you to be caring too much about
that. So instead,
what we need to think about way more
is the hook.
So we're going now into the reel setup.
The first thing that you should do
when you're facing the content block
is to work
backwards.
What is it in your business you need?
Is it to grow your email list?
Is it to grow your following? Because
that would be two very different tasks for
you to do.
If it's about growing your following,
maybe use some kind of social
trend or recent topic in the news
that you could talk about or react to.
But if it's about growing your email list,
maybe you need to be working with some
kind of chatbot to get some of your...
I'm going to say the last bit.
And actually,
you can keep in the fact I fucked up
that sentence, because I think
that could be good for people to see.
Or maybe it's the case
that you put out a piece of content that's
informative and
educative, and at the end of that,
connect some kind of chatbot where you say
to
people, "If you want this resource,
just DM or comment this word." Because the
type
of content that grows your page
and the type of content
that gets information from
your page are vastly different.
So depending on the goals,
working backwards, we
need to decide what we want to do.
Which moves us into the second thing.
If you were out there making a 10-hour
YouTube video. Fucked up again.
If you were out there making a 10-minute
YouTube video and the editor was allowed
to have one hour for every minute,
you might assume that
that editor would spend
one hour on minute one,
one hour on minute two,
one hour on minute three.
But what I actually get Declan to do
is to spend maybe 30,
40% of the edit on the first 30 seconds,
because that is so much
more important.
If you do not win someone over within the
first 30 seconds of a
YouTube edit,
what's the point of having great editing
at the back?
The same goes for an Instagram reel.
If you're going to spend half an hour
making a reel, you can allocate 15 minutes
to the first three to five seconds.
They are the first point of contact.
It's a bit like how you act on a first
date. You're overly polite.
You dress a little bit too smart.
You smell a little bit too good.
Because it's your first point of contact.
If you mess up the first date,
it doesn't matter if you want to go to the
Amalfi
Coast in three weeks. It's too late,
brother.
So work and ideate
and think up different things for your
hook.
And the last thing, to see what's working.
There is no harm to go look at other
creators in your niche and to see what's
working for them. Is it using a prop
when they talk about something?
Is it having a top-down camera
and illustrating on a whiteboard?
Because everything
that we have in content pretty much gets
stolen from someone.
This top-down camera here I got from Simon
Squit.
I saw that his videos
were doing outliers when he
was doing videos with content
creators on a top-down whiteboard. Now,
not only myself Copying it.
But Alex will mosey too.
So next time you have a content block,
just work backwards
to what your business needs.
Think about the campaign
that you want to do.
Look at some other creators,
see what's working for them.
Start with a strong hook,
solve someone's problem,
and you'll get everything you
need. Now,
that probably wasn't our best reel,
but it will give people a bit of an
insight into what happens. Then actually,
sometimes, I'll be honest with you, when
it comes to filming reels,
some of you out there will already know,
you'll go to
film and you will forget to connect your
microphone, or you will
get to the end and you weren't in focus.
And it's very frustrating at first
when you do this
when you're trying to film
content. But all you've got to do
is just gee yourself up
and hit record on the
camera again and go,
"Let's do one better."
Another thing that's really important for
when it comes to creating good content is
literally just writing down people's
problems.
Declan hit me, blindsided me with a niche.
Jewelry making. Nah, too niche.
Maybe we were saying someone that
has problems. A what?
An arborist.
What's an arborist?
Let's think about social media.
Let's think about a business,
because an arborist. That is quite niche,
actually.
Let's think about saying you'd use content
and social media for.
Yeah,
but a bricklayer only solves one problem.
What about an S&C coach?
Do I do too much fitness? Oh,
speech coach.
You put me on the spot there. Okay.
So I don't know.
I know there's a guy called Miles
Oshilade, I think his name is.
Need to do his speech coach thing,
actually.
I already know what these are going to be.
Saying "like" in content.
I did a podcast recently
and I listened back
and I just kept saying "like." I was
like, "Yeah, so like,
you could just do this, and then
if you do a chatbot, like,
people are just going to respond,
and then like,
you could just do..." Hated it.
Couldn't listen to it. Killed me.
One thing I believe speech coaches do
is they get
you comfortable with silence.
You ever notice that ums and uhs we use to
fill voids. So if someone says,
"What's your favorite thing about it?" You
go, "Um,
it's actually,
probably..." Whereas people,
you'll notice Chris
Williamson,
the guy who's definitely on steroids
and lying about it, he doesn't um
and uh. Have you ever noticed that?
He's had a speech coach. So yeah.
And also Jordan Peterson,
very good at this. You ask him something.
"Yeah,
I would agree with that." They're happy to
sit in silence, whereas
your classic uncouth scoundrels like me.
"Oh, God. God. Uh, yeah, basically,
like, uh, we..." It sounds horrible.
Let's say tone and projecting. Posture.
Planning.
What else?
Let's think about other problems people
have with speech. Accents.
Cool.
So these are just some of the problems
that I think a speech coach would
solve.
So we just need to turn one of these into
a hook.
And once we have a hook,
it's very easy to do the rest of the
video.
Let's think about this one.
Have you ever listened back to a
conversation that
you've made with someone
and heard the amount of times
that you've said "like"?
And like, at the time,
you didn't really realize, but like,
you're saying it quite
a lot and you're using it like a filler
word, and like, it's pretty normal
and most
people do it. But you know,
you could probably like,
say it a little bit less.
Straight away, people that
are self-conscious already of that
are going to listen
to that hook and be like, "Oh my God."
And then the setup could be, "Well,
in this
video, we're going to go through ways
that you can stop saying like, and start
speaking better instead." The second one.
So have you ever realized how many people
um and
uh? Because in speech,
it's just a normal thing.
People don't like listening to silence.
Well, guess what?
In this video,
I'm going to teach you ways
that you can banish and ban ums and uhs
from your vocabulary,
so you can not only sound smarter,
but you can lift up your
speech game. Tones and projecting.
When it comes to speaking,
the gravest error you can make
is to not talk loud
enough. And although you
are saying the same words, if you don't
say them in the right way, people
are not going to listen to what you're
saying.
Posture.
Did you know the way you sit can impact
the way that people perceive you
as a professional? Planning.
If you want to improve your retention
or improve your
ability to speak, the one thing
that people aren't telling you is that
if you plan
what you're going to speak about...
I don't know.
That could be more like a scripting
teleprompt or whatever. And then accents.
Margot Robbie and Chris Hemsworth had to
remove the Australianism out of their
accent. Did you know that?
So if you listen to Margot Robbie back in
the day when she's like at a state of
origin, she's like, "Yeah.
I'm Margot Robbie. I'm from Queensland.
My mom and dad wouldn't let me play
rugby." But now she's more Americanized.
Same as Chris Hemsworth.
And I'm pretty sure that Scottish
and Australian people,
so that people can understand what they're
saying, actually have to de-accent
themselves. So there, straight away,
just by listing down problems, you've
created hooks. Then I would go away
and make those six videos.
Then out of them,
they would all perform a different amount.
So let's say this one does 3K,
this one does 5K,
this one does 3K. This one does 11K, this
one does 9K. Actually, no,
we didn't like that one.
And then this one.
That could actually be the accent thing.
Did you know that Margot Robbie
and Chris Hemsworth had to learn to not
speak
Australian?
Then depending on the objection of your
business, you could say,
right, these two are outliers, posture
and accents.
So you could then go away
and make more videos on posture and
confidence.
Do you know there's some studies on
posture and hormones?
Although much of it has been debunked.
So there was a thing that
if you go into a toilet cubicle
and put your arms above
your head,
that it increases your testosterone.
They were done with saliva tests,
so I don't think they're accurate.
Posture and let's just say gravitas.
Then for this one, the accents. Accents,
Scottish,
Aus, USA. Because
when you start off with people's problems
and then you start creating solutions to
them, we're then going to see what people
have the interest in by the amount of
engagement they get.
Then to figure out if that's a fluke or
if it's actually a content bucket,
we would
then go away and make more content on
those to see whether or not this is
generally something people
are interested in or not.
Then if there's a certain subject
or content bucket that you talk about that
keeps getting engagement and interest,
you would probably then want to build out
some kind of product
or services for those people.
If we rewind to the very first slide where
I said we had the business mentorship
and we had content mastery,
inside the mentorship we've got loads of
different
threads. Getting leads, closing clients,
content, YouTube,
thumbnail ideation.
But the busiest thread
is the content thread.
So that gave me the idea to make a $99
course.
And then for short-form content mastery,
gets a 9% upsell
into the business mentorship.
If any of you are interested in that,
there are going
to be links in the description to
everything.
The last considerations we need to
consider within the content creation space
is this. CTA stands for call to action,
and call to action is
when we ask people to
do something. Even just then
when I spent 10 seconds talking about the
link in the
description. The majority of time,
people have been doing their call to
actions at
the end of a video. Now the issue is,
even for the best of us,
see how I said best
of us,
our retention graphs look like this.
The end of the video
is where the majority of people have left
So for any of you
out there,
if the purpose of your content
is to get email addresses or to get
people to look at your products,
we need a call to action in the middle of
the
video,
and Ed Lawrence has been doing amazing
work of telling people to put a call
to action in the first 90 seconds of a
video. And I've noticed a difference.
Traditionally,
people have left it to the very end of a
video for a call to action.
I think better off to do it earlier.
This is for Reels, this is for YouTube,
this is for everything.
The only thing we want to leave at the end
of a video is an end card.
And an end card is the opportunity for you
to promote another video.
That,
I think you do for the last 10 seconds of
a video, and your best way to get
someone to consider to clicking on an end
card is actually you have your initial
hook and introduction, you have a setup,
you have a payoff, then you can have
another hook at the end. Now,
because this video wasn't designed to sell
you
my products,
it was designed to be well packaged
and easy to get out there for
people to watch.
I actually now have the opportunity at the
end of the video to do
an end card. What I'm going to do
is go to YouTube.
I'm going to go to my YouTube Studio.
I'm going to go to Advanced mode.
Now here in Advanced mode,
we can add a metric called Subscribers
gained. Now, if we make this lifelong,
let's say the last
year,
we can see the video that's grown my
channel the most is Why I Quit My
Channel, with 421,000 subscribers.
So if the purpose of this video
is to get people to follow me, I now
know which one of my videos objectively
grows my page the
most. So to finish a video,
I would sit here,
I would have to point to one
side. Which side looks better, Declan?
This side or this side? This one.
And if you've made it to the end of this
video and ever wondered, James, why are
you posting on a YouTube channel that's
not even got 35,000
subscribers when you have another channel
with nearly half a million?
Well,
to find out why I completely quit
and went cold turkey on a channel with
nearly half a million subscribers,
this video here explains it perfectly.
See what I did? Ended with a hook.
That video is how the sausage is made.
Thanks for watching.